JOE: All children reach a range
of developmental milestones
between birth and adulthood.
Children with autism, however,
may reach some on time, or even
early, but lose ground later or
not reach some milestones at all.
Some may develop skills that are
very advanced, but not the useful
ones they need in everyday life.
BETH: here are, a few developmental
markers that are most likely
and most obvious when a child
has autism spectrum disorder.
Problems such as working simple toys, not
speaking in sentences, not understanding
simple instructions, not playing as
others and the lack of eye contact.
JOE: The physical changes of
puberty can have an alarming
impact on individuals with autism.
With girls, their breasts develop, and the
menstruation starts, with boys their voice
gets lower, and the penis grows larger.
BETH: Girls may struggle with the
concept of periods but should be shown
that it is a natural process and not to
be concerned, and they should be shown
how to use feminine hygiene products.
Boys should equally be told about
nighttime ejaculation and erections
so as to allay their fears.
JOE: Both should be instructed through
personal hygiene routines and why this
is more important as they progress
through puberty to become an adult.
These could be done by means of visual
supports such as pictures and diagrams.
During puberty, most individuals
start to experience sexual urges
and It’s normal for children on the
spectrum to feel sexually aroused.
BETH: For teens with autism associated
sensory issues, these new sensations
can cause anxiety as they don’t know
how to handle these new sensations.
Masturbation, is a healthy and normal
part of development, however, some
teens on the autism spectrum lack
the social awareness skills to know
when and where it’s not appropriate.